(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-07-29T22:42:51.048966",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.6-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ミラクル重大発表祭り らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ
Miracle Major Announcement Festival: Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live
いよーっ！
Yo---!
ストレイト ドキドキする
Straight, my heart is racing
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing straight through my heart
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
実る果実が水を弾いて
Ripening fruit repels water droplets
キラキラしてる光に似てる
Looking just like a glittering light
グラウンドに立つキミの姿が
The sight of you standing on the field
まぶしくて少し照れちゃうけど
Is so dazzling it makes me a little shy, but
ストレイト まっすぐだね
Straight, so direct
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love must surely be a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing straight through my heart
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ秘密の光
A secret light connecting the two of us
あの日見つけた秘密の光
That secret light we found on that day
恋の瞬間 音は止まって
In the moment of love, sound stands still
時間はスローリーに 恋の光線
Time slows down in a ray of love
ストレイト ドキドキする
Straight, my heart is racing
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is just like a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing straight through my heart
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ストレイト まっすぐだね
Straight, so direct
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love must surely be a laser beam
心をシュワりと突き刺すの
Piercing straight through my heart
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
イヨーッ！
Yo!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Step right up, come one and all!
始まりましたらでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！今宵はまだまだこれから！皆さん一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Welcome to Raden's new outfit 3D live reveal! Tonight's just getting started! Let's get hyped together, everyone!
尽きない好奇心
An endless curiosity
素晴らしきジャポニズムに触れて 令和の風雲児 皆々にお届けいたしましょう
Touching upon wonderful Japonism, a figure of the Reiwa era shall deliver it to you all!
饒舌に情熱 伝えたい愛に溢れている
Eloquently and passionately overflowing with love to share
無知の知がきっと 素敵な始まりになるんだよ
Knowing what you don't know will surely be a wonderful start
知って欲しい たらふく味わって 尊い人生
I want you to know, to savor fully this precious life
紐解いた歴史に 心惹かれていく
My heart grows captivated by history unraveled
遥か遠く 電波に乗って あなたまで
Riding the airwaves far into the distance, reaching out to you
この想い 純粋に伝えたい
I want to purely convey these feelings
新しい世界 見せてあげる
I'll show you a brand-new world
開口一番やっちゃって 破天荒に型破って打ち立てる金字塔 パンチライン 時を超え 出囃子に乗せて
Setting the stage right off the bat, breaking molds in unprecedented style, erecting a monumental achievement, a punchline transcending time, set to the entrance music!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Step right up, come one and all!
はい はい
Yeah, yeah!
はい
Yeah!
はい はい
Yeah, yeah!
はい
Yeah!
浪漫を抱いた人生を
Embracing a life filled with romance,
丸ごと賭けて傾きましょう
let's bet it all and live with flair!
刹那に生きた足跡を
The footsteps left in fleeting moments,
偉大な先人と共に
together with great predecessors.
洒落た口火切って
Sparking stylish beginnings,
手招く芸事の深淵
beckoning to the depths of the arts.
相反する感情 愛憎
Conflicting emotions of love and hate,
超えていく感動
moving beyond to pure emotion.
遥か遠く世界超え 宇宙まで
Far beyond the world, even unto space,
この想い 果てしなく届けたい
I want to send these feelings without end!
オリエンタル
Oriental,
アクシデンタル
Occidental,
どちらも愛しちゃって
loving them both!
掻き立てる衝動が加速する
Stirred-up impulses accelerate,
創造の世界へと飛び込んで
diving into a world of creation!
小噺に乗せて
Riding on a short story,
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
come on over, step right up and see!
語り継いでく 人世の想い
Passing down the feelings of human life,
あなたの心に 寄り添って
nestling close to your heart.
道楽主義で
With a pleasure-seeking spirit,
小粋になせ
living with refined style,
そんな生き様 如何ですか？
how do you like a way of life like this?
遥か遠く 電波に乗って あなたまで
Riding the airwaves far and wide to you,
この想い 純粋に伝えたい
I purely want to convey these feelings,
新しい世界 見せてあげる
I'll show you a brand new world!
開口一番 やっちゃって
Right off the bat, let's go all out,
破天荒に 型破って 打ち立てる
unprecedented, breaking the mold, establishing...
金字塔 パンチライン 時を超え
...a monumental work, a punchline transcending time!
出囃子に乗せて 寄ってらっしゃい
Riding the entrance music, come on over,
見てらっしゃい 寄ってらっしゃい
step right up and see! Come on over,
見てらっしゃい！
step right up and see!
はい はい
Yeah, yeah!
はい
Yeah!
はい はい
Yeah, yeah!
はい！ということで！
Alright! And with that!
ということで、始まりました！
And with that, it has officially begun!
儒烏風亭らデン 新衣装お披露目ライブ！
Juufuutei Raden's New Outfit Reveal Live!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様あらためまして、こんばんは！
Alright, everyone, once again, good evening!
ホロライブデバイス、ReGLOSSの新進気鋭のミュージアムプリンセス担当、儒烏風亭一門は前座見習い...
From hololive DEV_IS ReGLOSS, in charge of being the up-and-coming Museum Princess, and an apprentice opening act of the Juufuutei school...
ちょっと待って！
Wait a second!
儒烏風亭らでんでございます！
It's Juufuutei Raden!
みんな来てくれて、ありがとうございます！
Thank you all so much for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは... ハッシュタグ「らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」で、いっぱいポストしてくれると、とっても嬉しいです！よろしくお願いします！
Today's hashtag... if you could post a lot using #らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ, I'd be super happy! Please do!
ちょっと待って、「大丈夫？」って言われてます。大丈夫です！ありがとうございます！
Wait, people are asking "Are you okay?". I'm okay! Thank you!
さあ、今回ね、らでん3Dお披露目ライブ... 新衣装お披露目ライブ、ミラクル重大発表祭り！タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表が...
So today, during Raden's 3D... New Outfit Reveal Live Miracle Major Announcement Festival! As the title says, there seem to be major announcements...
あるとか、ないとか...！しかも、1つだけじゃないの！
There might or might not be...! And not just one!
ということで、今日はね、ぜひ最後までお楽しみください！
So, please enjoy until the very end today!
さあ、そして皆様、気になってますよね？この新衣装！いかがですか？
And everyone, you're curious about it, right? This new outfit! How is it?
どう？みんなどうかな？これが私、らでんの新衣装、「ミュージアムプリンセス」衣装です！どう？
How is it? What do you all think? This is my, Raden's, new outfit—the "Museum Princess" outfit! How is it?
どうかな？どうかな？どうかな、みんな？
How is it? How is it? What do you think, everyone?
ちょっとね、今日ね、ラグがね... ちょっとコメントとのラグがあって、アレなんですけれども...
Today there's a bit of lag... a slight lag with the comments, so...
良い？良い？ありがとう！
Good? Good? Thank you!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
「可愛い」、ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
"Cute", thank you! Thank you so much!
今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、サクラショウリ先生にお仕立ていただきましたー！イエーイ！
This time, to celebrate reaching 1 million subscribers, it was designed by Shouri Sakura-sensei! Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです！本当にありがとう！ありがとうございます！
This is all thanks to everyone who always supports me! Thank you so much! Thank you very much!
もちろんね、このライブの後、アンコールライブっていうのがメン限であるんですけれども、そこでまた、のんびりとこのお衣装について、詳しくね、見ていきたいと思いますので、気になるよって方はぜひ...
Of course, after this live stream, there's an encore stream on the members-only channel, where we'll take a closer, relaxed look at this outfit, so if you're curious, please...
ぜひ、メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
I hope you consider joining the membership.
今日ね、お昼くらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプも追加されましたので、ぜひコメント欄で良かったら使ってみてください。
Today around noon, new member emotes were added, so feel free to use them in the comments!
もうみんな使いたくてたまらないアロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、ぜひ皆さんでね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください！よろしくお願いします！
Emotes like the Arowana that everyone's been dying to use were added, so please flood the comments with Arowana! Thank you so much!
さあ、ということで、お衣装、改めて新衣装なんですが、
Now then, as for the outfit—once again, this new outfit—
今回衣装のほかに、ちょっとね、一つ、助かるものも作りましたよ〜。
along with the outfit, I also made something super helpful!
ま、楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども。
Well, it actually appeared during the song earlier, but...
ジャンジャカジャンジャンジャンジャン、あ、あ、逆、あ、あ、あ、ジャン！
Tada-da-da-da-da! Ah, it's backwards... Ah, tada!
素敵でございます！
Isn't it wonderful?
いいでしょう、これ！かっこいいでしょう！今回ね、特注でステッキ作っちゃった〜！
Great, isn't it? Looks cool, right? I had a custom cane made this time!
しかも、これだけじゃないんですよ！
And that's not all!
見ててね！
Watch this!
らでんビーム！
Raden Beam!
うわー！レーザービームだ！すごい！
Woah! It's a laser beam! Awesome!
今回ね、あの、レーザービーム出せるようにしてもらいました！
I had them make it able to shoot laser beams this time!
もう大丈夫です。疲れた。
Okay, that's enough. I'm tired.
いかん、もう今日はね、ライブまだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。
Oh no, the live show is just getting started today, so I need to save my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力がもう空っぽになるまで、全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくね！
But today, I'll be giving it my all until my stamina is completely empty, so everyone, please cheer me on!
それではそろそろ、次の曲に行きたいと、思います。
Now then, I think it's time to move on to the next song.
さあ、次の曲は何なのか、重大発表とは何なのか、ワクワクしながら聞いてくださいね。
What will the next song be? What is the major announcement? Listen along with excitement!
そしてここからは、ゲストも登場します！ゲストパートは収録になりますので、悪しからず！
And from here on, guests will be appearing! Please note that the guest segment is pre-recorded!
それでは、今宵はまだまだ始まったばかり！みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
Tonight has only just begun! Let's all enjoy it together!
それでは、どうぞ！
Here you go!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, boundlessly,
明日へと導くよ
it leads to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to shine my own light!
DIVE!
WOW... WOW... WOW...
自信なくしてただ 心に鍵かけて
Lacking confidence, I locked up my heart,
響く自分の声に 耳塞いでた
covering my ears to my echoing voice.
本当はいつだって 分かっていたんだよ
Truth is, I knew all along
一番大切なもの ここにあること
that the most precious thing is right here.
無限に広がる宇宙 迷わず進もう
In this infinitely expanding universe, let me move forward without hesitation!
Go! Fly! Yes! Go High!
目を閉じて 言い聞かせてみたってもう
Even if I close my eyes and try to convince myself,
体中騒いでる 止まらない 強く
my whole body is buzzing—it won't stop, growing stronger!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, boundlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
the future I embraced turns into a miracle!
生まれた思いが 明日へと導くよ
The feelings that were born lead to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to shine my own light!
DIVE!
WOW... WOW... WOW...
誰のものでもない 心に問いかけて
Belonging to no one else, asking my heart,
選んだ道の先へと まっすぐに
straight toward the end of the path I chose!
どんな時だって 見失わないよ
No matter when, I won't lose sight of it,
一番大切な場所を見つけたから
because I found the most important place.
遠回りでもいい 胸張って進もう
Taking a detour is fine, let's march forward with pride!
Louder! Say louder!
不器用かな でも傷ついたって構わないよ
Clumsy as I am, I don't care if I get hurt!
曇りない気持ちで生きたい 私らしく
I want to live with unclouded feelings, true to myself!
両手を広げて
Spreading both hands wide,
解き放した昨日が 翼になる
the yesterday I unleashed becomes my wings.
重ねた出会いが...
The encounters piled up...
この瞬間
This moment,
この時彩るよ
I'll color this time,
私だけの光信じて
Believing in my own light...
DIVE!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, boundlessly,
抱きしめた未来が奇跡になる
The future I embraced will become a miracle.
生まれた思いが明日へと導くよ
The feelings born within will lead to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to unleash my own light!
DIVE!
WOW WOW...
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！アート！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Nailing every test!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's MEM-O-RIZE!
JAPANの美術史お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW! 3Dライブの途中ではございますが、ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います！
Let's Memorize Japanese Art History SHOW! We're in the middle of our 3D live, but now let's start our lesson on Japanese art history!
は～い皆さんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hello, everyone! Time to learn art history!
まずは縄文・弥生・古墳までやってみよう！
First, let's cover Jomon, Yayoi, and Kofun!
火焔型土器、遮光器土偶、縄文のビーナス！
Flame-style pottery, Shakoki-dogu, Venus of Jomon!
銅鐸、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器！
Dotaku, bronze spears, bronze swords, Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、掛甲武人、馬型埴輪！
Various Haniwa: Dancing Figures, Warrior in Armor, and Horse Haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に土師器・須恵器！
Iron swords from tombs, Seven-Branched Sword, Hajiki and Sueki pottery!
OK OK OK OK いい感じ！
OK OK OK OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！ 3! 2! 1! GO!
Next are Asuka and Nara periods! 3! 2! 1! GO!
仏像いっぱい 釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像！
Lots of Buddha statues! Shaka Nyorai, with Bodhisattvas for Triad Statues!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画！
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Shucho, Kondo Wall Paintings, Tomb Murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像！
Great Buddha at Todai-ji, Asura statue at Kofuku-ji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！ 螺鈿紫檀五弦琵琶！
Let's play with sound! Raden Shitan no Gogen Biwa!
未来のキミに届くように 繋いでいこう この想い
To reach the future you, let me connect these feelings!
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう刻が来るまで
As long as there's love, it'll be fine, until the time comes to share them.
JAPANの美術史♪ (アート！アート！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (絵画に立体！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪ (テストもバッチリ！)
Japanese Art History♪ (Nailing every test!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's MEM-O-RIZE!
まだまだ色々ございます！がんばってついてきてくださいね！
There's still so much more! Do your best to keep up!
平安・鎌倉・南北朝！ 参る！
Heian, Kamakura, Nanboku-cho! Here we go!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り！
Mandala, Ichiboku-zukuri, Yosegi-zukuri!
鳥獣人物戯画に源氏物語！
Choju-jinbutsu-giga and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像！
Seated Amida Nyorai Statue at Byodoin Phoenix Hall!
模様がとってもかわいい 片輪車螺鈿手箱！
Super cute patterns! Katawaguruma Raden Tebako!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像！
Kongo Rikishi Statues at Todai-ji's Nandaimon Gate!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図！
Amida Twenty-Five Bodhisattvas Welcoming Diagram, Yamagoshi Amida Diagram!
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像！
Moko Shurai Ekotoba, Statue of Monk Kuya!
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻！
Ippen Shonin Eden, Picture Scroll of the Latter Three Years' War!
YOYO! 半分くらい来たぜ多分！
YOYO! We're probably about halfway there!
まだまだいくぜ、ありのまま！ 室町から安土桃山！
Still going strong, just as we are! From Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面・翁に枯山水！
Noh masks, Okina, and Karesansui gardens!
天橋立図、呂洞賓図！
Amanohashidate Diagram, Lu Dongbin Diagram!
狩野派の屏風！
Kano School Folding Screens!
曜変天目茶碗！
Yohen Tenmoku Tea Bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風！
Scenes in and around Capital Folding Screen!
唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図！
Chinese Lion Folding Screen, Pine and Hawk Diagram!
職人尽図、花下遊楽図！
Shokunin Zukushi-zu, Kakayuraku-zu!
松林図、山水図、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱 本物？！
Pine Trees Screen, Landscape Diagram, Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Inkstone Box... The real thing?!
未来のキミに届くように 繋いでいこう この想い
To reach the future you, let me connect these feelings!
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう刻が来るまで
As long as there's love, it'll be fine, until the time comes to share them.
ここまでついてきてくれてありがとう！ なんと今回特別に！バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱さんに来ていただきました！ ありがとうございます！ さあ、最後！江戸時代から昭和まで！いきますよ！
Thank you for sticking with me this far! And as a special treat today, the Virtual Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Inkstone Box is here! Thank you so much! Now for the finale, Edo period to Showa! Here we go!
あとちょっと、最後まで頑張ろう！ 3! 2! 1! GO!
Just a bit left, let's do our best until the end! 3! 2! 1! GO!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱！
Funabashi Maki-e Inkstone Box!
風神雷神図屏風！
Wind God and Thunder God Screens!
燕子花図屏風！
Irises Screen!
見返り美人！
Beauty Looking Back!
好色一代男...
Life of an Amorous Man...
奥の細道
Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景
Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji
東海道中膝栗毛
Tokaidouchuu Hizakurige
老猿、ゆあみ、坑夫
Old Monkey, Bathing, Miner
墓守、伎芸天
Grave Keeper, Gigeiten
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Harvest of the Sea
渡頭の夕暮
Sunset at a Ferry
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Smile of Reiko, The Forbidden City
斑猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, Angler at Izura
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun
吉原治良の円
Jiro Yoshihara's Circle
東山魁夷の道
Kaii Higashiyama's Road
未来のキミに届くように
Reaching out to you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass down these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be alright,
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
so let's talk until morning comes,
未来まで
all the way into the future!
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN's Art History♪
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
O-BO-E-MA-SHOW!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
Good evening to everyone watching this stream.
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで らでんの小噺美術解説のお時間です！
We're in the middle of the stream, but it's time for Raden's Art Explanation Chat!
なんと、今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでーん！
What we're introducing today is right here! Ta-da!
国宝「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」ということで…
National Treasure "Inkstone Box with Eight-Bridge Diagram in Maki-e and Raden Inlay"...
今回 特別にも東京国立博物館さんから 3Dモデルをお借りしましたー！
For this occasion, we specially borrowed a 3D model from Tokyo National Museum!
みんなにもよく見てもらいましょう こちらでございます！
Let's take a closer look at it together. Here it is!
こちらが バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱です！
This is the virtual Inkstone Box with Eight-Bridge Diagram in Maki-e and Raden Inlay!
「螺鈿」ってなんかどこかで聞いたことがありますね。 そんな名前のVTuberがいるような、いなかったような…
"Raden"... I feel like I've heard that somewhere before. Like there's a VTuber by that name... or maybe not...
こちらは 私のオリジナル曲 『JAPANの美術史♪お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!』にも 登場する作品です。
This artwork is also featured in my original song "JAPAN's Art History ♪ O-BO-E-MA-SHOW!"
どうですか、皆さん？ この輝きとデザイン！ 大胆かつ 花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品。
How do you like it, everyone? Look at this shine and design! Bold, yet with delicate and beautiful flower petal decorations.
作ったのは 尾形光琳という人です。
It was created by a craftsman named Ogata Korin.
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、 どこかモダンな様子も感じることができます。
He made this inkstone box during the Edo period, but it has a surprisingly modern feel to it.
さて、工芸品を見るとき 様々な見方がありますが、 手助けになるのは「作品名」です。
Now, when looking at crafts, there are various ways to appreciate them, but a helpful clue is the "title".
この工芸品の名前を復習しましょう。 「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」
Let's review the title of this piece again: "Inkstone Box with Eight-Bridge Diagram in Maki-e and Raden Inlay".
漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきます。 まずは「八橋」。
There are a lot of kanji, but let's break it down one by one. First, "Yatsuhashi" (Eight-Bridge).
日本美術史における工芸品は 物語の一場面や 和歌がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
In Japanese art history, crafts are often themed around scenes from stories or waka poems.
そして、この硯箱もその一つ。
And this inkstone box is one of them.
『伊勢物語』第九段「三河国八橋」の場面が 主題になっているんですよ。
It takes its subject from Chapter 9 of "The Tales of Ise", "Yatsuhashi in Mikawa Province".
なので これは橋ですね。「八橋」 この場面に出てくる八つの橋のこと。
So these are bridges! "Yatsuhashi" refers to the eight bridges in this scene.
つまりは 何を描いたかを表しています。 では 何を描いたかが分かったら、次に
In other words, it shows *what* is depicted. Once we know what is drawn, next is...
どんな技法が使われたか。 それを表すのが「蒔絵」、そして「螺鈿」です。
...what *techniques* were used. That is shown by "Maki-e" and "Raden".
「蒔絵」とは簡単に言うと、 金の粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。
Simply put, "Maki-e" is applying gold powder using lacquer as an adhesive.
ここで言うと カキツバタの葉っぱの部分ですね。 ぴんぴんとなっている部分です。
Here, it refers to the leaves of the Japanese irises—these parts pointing upward.
次に「螺鈿」とは 貝の光沢のある部分を薄くして貼り付けたもの。
Next, "Raden" is slicing the shiny parts of shells thin and inlaying them.
ここで言うと カキツバタのお花の部分です。
Here, it refers to the flowers of the irises.
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、 花びらを表現するために あえて穴の開いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Abalone shells are used in this piece, and you can see he deliberately used shells with holes to express the petals.
そして最後に そもそもこれは何か？ それを表すのが「硯箱」です。
And finally, what is this object in the first place? That's what "Suzuribako" (Inkstone Box) tells us.
真ん中をご覧ください。 こちら 墨汁を作る硯入れが上の段にあり、
Look at the center. Here on the upper tray is the compartment for holding the inkstone used to make ink,
さらにその段の下、下の段は料紙、 紙入れになっています。
and below that tray, the lower compartment is used for storing paper.
さあ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の 言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
Now, we've finished breaking down all the terms in "Inkstone Box with Eight-Bridge Diagram in Maki-e and Raden Inlay"!
カキツバタが咲く川にかかる橋の ダイナミックな魅力にも大注目なこの硯箱。
Pay close attention to the dynamic charm of the bridges over the river where irises bloom!
パカッと開けると 波が描かれています。
When you pop it open, waves are drawn inside.
もうここまで聞いたら なぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか 皆さんならお分かりですね？
After hearing all this, I'm sure you understand why wave patterns were placed inside, right?
上の段にある橋の 下の…
It's what lies beneath the bridge on the upper tray...
波ということですね
So it represents waves, doesn't it?
実はこちらの「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」
Actually, this "Yatsuhashi Makie Raden Inkstone Box"...
普段展示される際は 箱を閉じた状態なんですよ
is usually displayed with its lid closed.
つまり 中の様子をご覧いただけるのは この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
In other words, seeing the inside like this is a rare opportunity exclusive to this stream!
こちらがなんと 2026年5月26日から8月16日
This will actually be displayed from May 26 to August 16, 2026,
東京国立博物館 本館2室にて展示されるとのことで
in Gallery 2 of the Main Building at Tokyo National Museum,
ぜひ見ていっていただければと思います！
so I hope you'll definitely check it out!
このね 波のね 細かいところが...
The delicate details of these waves...
これ筆でやってるんですからね！筆でこうやって...
were done with a brush, you know! With a brush, like this...
あっ お時間となってしまいました！
Ah, it looks like time is up!
それでは皆様 また次回お会いいたしましょう！
Well then, everyone, see you next time!
特報 その①
[Special News Part 1]
儒鳥風亭らてん × 東京国立博物館
[Juuteutei Raden × Tokyo National Museum]
未来の君に届くように
So that it reaches you in the future,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's connect these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, it's alright.
重なり合おう 明日（あす）が来るまで
Let's overlap together until tomorrow comes.
ということで なんと！
And so, guess what!
私 儒鳥風亭らてんと 東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
A collaboration between me, Juuteutei Raden, and Tokyo National Museum has been confirmed!
すごーい！みんなやったよー！
Amazing! We did it, everyone!
もうね らてん配信とか いろんなところで東博さんがね ずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけれども
I've been saying on my streams and everywhere else how much I love TNM,
今回ね 念願の東博・らてんコラボでございます！すごい！
and now my long-cherished dream of a TNM x Raden collaboration is happening! Amazing!
あら 東博 最近... 名前聞きましたね
Oh, TNM... you heard that name recently, right?
そうです！先日ね 10月から京都 1月から東京にて
That's right! Just the other day, starting October in Kyoto and January in Tokyo...
開催予定の特別展「源氏物語 王朝のかがやき」展の音声ガイドのスペシャルナビゲーターを務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが
it was announced that I'll serve as the audio guide special navigator for the upcoming special exhibition "The Tale of Genji: Radiant Culture of the Japanese Imperial Court"...
これね これチラシね
This, look, this flyer!
なんと この特別展「源氏物語」展の東京会場となる...
And guess what, at the Tokyo venue for this "Tale of Genji Exhibition"...
ごめんなさい笑
Sorry! (laughs)
東京国立博物館様とのコラボが決定いたしました！すごい！
A collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum has been decided! Amazing!
開催時期はこの「源氏物語」展と同じ 2027年1月に実施予定となっております！
It's scheduled to take place in January 2027, the same time as "The Tale of Genji Exhibition"!
なんで こっちは「源氏物語」展・儒鳥風亭らてんコラボ そして同じ1月に...
So, over here we have "The Tale of Genji Exhibition" x Juuteutei Raden collaboration, and in the same January...
東京国立博物館・儒鳥風亭らてんコラボがあると！
we also have the Tokyo National Museum x Juuteutei Raden collaboration!
もっと簡単に言うと 来年の1月は東博の色んなところにらてんちゃんが出没しちゃいます！っていう感じです！
To put it simply, next January, Raden-chan will be popping up all over TNM! That's what it means!
こちら詳細につきましては また続報をお待ちいただければと思います！
As for the details, please stay tuned for further updates!
凄いでしょう！すごいすごい！
Isn't that amazing? Amazing, amazing!
ということで 本日の重大発表1つ目は 東博・儒鳥風亭らてんコラボでございました！みんなありがとー！
So, the first major announcement for today was the TNM × Juuteutei Raden collaboration! Thank you, everyone!
さあ ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます！
Now then, the live performance and major announcements are still going to continue!
ちょっと待って... ちょっと疲れた笑
Wait a second... I got a little tired! (laughs)
ということでね 東博... 元々らてんが日本美術史に興味を持ったのって 東博さんで能面を見て
You know, TNM... the original reason Raden became interested in Japanese art history was seeing Noh masks at TNM,
その時に「ああ なんて美しいんだ」って思ったし
and back then, I thought, "Ah, how beautiful!"
らてんって日本で生まれ育ったのに 日本のこと本当に何も知らなかったんだなって思ったのがきっかけで
Realizing that even though I was born and raised in Japan, I really knew nothing about Japan was what sparked it all.
そこからなんやかんやあって 日本美術史を勉強したりして
From there, one thing led to another, and I started studying Japanese art history,
なんやかんやあって ホロライブに入って
one thing led to another, and I joined Hololive,
なんやかんやあって 今こんな素敵なお衣装をお披露目して
one thing led to another, and now I'm unveiling this wonderful outfit,
なんやかんやあって こんなありがたいコラボをさせていただける事になりました！
and one thing led to another, resulting in this incredible collaboration!
みんなのおかげだよー！ありがとうー！
It's all thanks to everyone! Thank you!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません！
Life really is unpredictable! You never know what's going to happen!
とんでもない... 何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのか みたいなことも分かりません
It's crazy... you can't tell how things will connect to the future.
人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなものでございますな！
Life is like a bizarre adventure, isn't it?
さあ ということで そろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います！
Well then, with that, it's about time to move on to the next song!
それではお聞きください 『ココロパズルリズム』
Please listen: "Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm".
Ah...
Ah~
ココロのパズル
Puzzle of the heart
ココロのリズム
Rhythm of the heart
ココロのパズル
Puzzle of the heart
ココロのリズム
Rhythm of the heart
これからの未来 ほら たくさんのピース
Look, so many pieces of the future ahead
組み立てるのは キミ次第
How to assemble them is up to you
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living through each tomorrow one by one
ココロのパズルと リズム
The puzzle and rhythm of the heart
うまくは言えないけれど
I can't put it into words very well, but...
不思議と安心できて
...strangely, I feel at ease...
いられる感覚って
...and this feeling of being able to stay like this...
まるでパズルみたいだ
...is just like a puzzle.
もうずっと前から
From way back when,
僕らは予約席
we've had reserved seats.
さあ 両手つないで
Come on, let's hold hands,
きっと一つになれる
and we can surely become one.
完成が見えていても
Even if the complete picture is in sight,
すんなりとはいかないね
it doesn't always go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each one is a fragment of a dream.
これからの未来 ほら たくさんのピース
Look, so many pieces of the future ahead
組み立てるのは キミ次第
How to assemble them is up to you
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living through each tomorrow one by one
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but...
それよりも大切なのは
...what's even more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is when we're sad or happy...
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのパズル
...being able to cry together in that heart's puzzle.
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't always go smoothly, does it?
キミと僕の パズルの行方
Where the puzzle of you and me is headed...
これからの LOVE STORY ほら たくさんのピース
Look, so many pieces in our love story ahead
間違えることもあるけれど
We might make mistakes along the way, but...
胸に刻み 明日を生きる
...etching them in our hearts, we live tomorrow.
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but...
それよりも大切なのは
...what's even more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is when we're sad or happy...
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのリズム
...being able to cry together in that heart's rhythm.
don't cry don't cry
walk hand in hand
ah ah 繋いで
ah ah, holding hands,
it's a nice day
これからの未来 ほら たくさんのピース
Look, so many pieces of the future ahead
組み立てるのは キミ次第
How to assemble them is up to you
一つずつの 明日を生きる
Living through each tomorrow one by one
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいことも きっとあるけど
There will surely be fun times too, but...
それよりも大切なのは
...what's even more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is when we're sad or happy...
一緒に泣ける そんなココロのパズル
...being able to cry together in that heart's puzzle.
ココロのリズム
Rhythm of the heart
Ah~
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中でございますが、ここで、らでんの小噺美術解説の時間で〜す！
We're in the middle of the live, but now it's time for Raden's short art commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは...
What I'm introducing today is...
こちらで〜す！ジャジャン！
This one right here! Ta-da!
クロード・モネ「睡蓮の池」
Claude Monet, "Water Lily Pond"
今回なんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！本当にありがとうございます！
This time, we have borrowed this image from The National Gallery in London! Thank you so much!
皆さんどうですか？私モネの描く世界が大好きなんです。
Everyone, how do you like it? I absolutely love the world Monet paints.
まぁモネと言えば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが、彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか？
Monet is a very popular painter in Japan as well, but what makes his paintings so captivating?
今回は彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょー！
Today, let's put into words the inherent charm of his paintings!
この作品は1899年頃描かれました。
This work was painted around 1899.
緑色の光があふれる睡蓮の池には大きな橋がかかり、橋の奥には柳が描かれています。
In the water lily pond overflowing with green light, a large bridge spans across, and behind the bridge, willows are depicted.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this place is a pond that Monet built at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという町に家を購入した彼は、近隣の川から水を引いて...
After buying a house in the town of Giverny, France, he diverted water from a nearby river...
...自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
...to create his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋、これいわゆる太鼓橋と呼ばれる橋と、柳。
A large arched bridge—what is known as a drum bridge—and willows.
あれ？なんだか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Wait, doesn't it feel somehow Japanese?
それもそのはず。彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
And for good reason. He was a painter heavily influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e prints.
彼の描く絵は光にあふれていて、目の前で風が吹いて水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
His paintings are filled with light, making it look as if the wind is blowing and the water's surface is rippling right before your eyes.
じーっと見ていると、水も花も木も橋も空気でさえも溶けていくようです。見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
As you stare closely, everything seems to melt together. Don't you think it's a soothing painting to look at?
モネは絵を描くとき、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく、純粋な何にも混ざっていない色を置くように塗りました。
When Monet painted, instead of mixing colors, he applied pure, unmixed colors side by side.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど、塗り重ねれば重ねるほど暗くなっていきます。彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し、光であふれた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
The more you mix colors, the darker they become. He solved this by placing colors side by side, succeeding in creating paintings full of light.
この絵画に近づいてみると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
If you step closer to this painting, the brushstrokes remain clearly visible.
隣り合った絵の具一つ一つの相乗効果を計算し、絵の具の塊から温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は、モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
By calculating the synergy of adjacent colors, he turned paint into landscapes that evoke temperature and humidity—a technique he researched all his life.
光を求めたモネが、陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く引かれたのも理解できますね。
It's easy to understand why Monet, who sought light, was so strongly drawn to shadowless Japanese ukiyo-e prints.
彼の絵画の明るさは画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱すら感じられる作品だと私は感じます。
The brightness of his paintings is the fruit of his research as an artist, emanating true passion.
みんなはこの絵画、どう読んだかな？
How did all of you interpret this painting?
実はモネは「印象派」の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、それはまた別のお話。
In fact, Monet was also the person who triggered Impressionism, but that's a story for another time.
と言った感じでございまして、こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！ぜひ行ってみてください！また次回！
And that's the story! You can view this work at The National Gallery in London! Please go see it! See you next time!
(I want to fight your brother) let's kung-fu!
EVERYNIGHT I LOOK TO THE SKIES AND WONDER WHAT WE DID ALWAYS A NAIVE POINT OF VIEW THAT BREAKS US IN THE END
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did / Always a naive point of view that breaks us in the end
IF I COULD FIND THE MEANING OF IT ALL I'D TAKE THE CHANCE MAYBE IN TIME WE'LL WALK THE MILE AND CHANGE IT IF WE CAN
If I could find the meaning of it all I'd take the chance / Maybe in time we'll walk the mile and change it if we can
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR) ALWAYS
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START) ALWAYS
(NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN) ALWAYS
WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
AROUND THE WORLD 新しいことに
Around the world to something new
AROUND THE WORLD フミダスチカラで
Around the world with the courage to step forward
AROUND THE WORLD 世界は変わるさ
Around the world the world will change
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
(let's kung-fu!)
果てしなく広がるこの大地を 僕らはまた...
Across this endlessly spreading earth, we will keep walking once again...
果てなく広がる この大地を 僕らはまた 歩き続けるさ
We will keep walking on this vast, endless land.
全ての意味が 分かるのならば
If I can understand the meaning of everything,
この瞳で 何を見つめるのだろう
what will I gaze upon with these eyes?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR NA~)
ALWAYS
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START NA~)
(NEVER HOLD ME DOWN NA~)
ALWAYS
WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
AROUND THE WORLD 君だけのために
AROUND THE WORLD, just for you.
AROUND THE WORLD 探し続けるよ
AROUND THE WORLD, I'll keep searching.
AROUND THE WORLD 奇跡のかけらを
AROUND THE WORLD, for pieces of miracles.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
Yeah ey AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE RAINING AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE HARD
AS LONG AS WE TRUST EACH OTHER
NOTHING'S GONNA BREAK APART OH NO! NO!
IF YA WANNA BE SOMEBODY
GET UP ON YA FEET AND GO
I KNOW WE'RE GONNA MEET EACH OTHER SOMEWHERE AROUND THE GLOBE
AROUND THE WORLD いつでも自分に
AROUND THE WORLD, always to myself.
AROUND THE WORLD 負けている人は
AROUND THE WORLD, those who lose to themselves...
AROUND THE WORLD 何も掴めない
AROUND THE WORLD, can grab hold of nothing.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK! BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
特報 その②
[Special News Part 2]
儒烏風亭らデン × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
Juufuutei Raden x THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
儒烏風亭らデン ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリー コラボ決定!!
Juufuutei Raden x London National Gallery Collaboration Confirmed!!
儒烏風亭らデンの瞳に映る世界の名画 A SHARED ART JOURNEY
World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes: A SHARED ART JOURNEY
5/20(水)12:00より グッズの予約販売が開始
Pre-orders for merchandise begin May 20th (Wed) at 12:00.
はい！
Alright!
ということで なんと 私 儒烏風亭らでんと
So, believe it or not, I, Juufuutei Raden, and...
ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
a collaboration with the National Gallery, London, has been officially decided!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんと言えば もうね ゴッホ ターナー
Speaking of the National Gallery, they have Monet, van Gogh, Turner...
もうとにかくいろんな画家さんたちの 超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが
strictly speaking, so many famous works by various artists are housed there.
なんとそんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ！
And now, a collaboration with that very National Gallery!
「儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画」
"World Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes...
-A SHARED ART JOURNEY- コラボ決定です！ すごい！
-A SHARED ART JOURNEY-" collaboration is happening! Incredible!
さあ これね とある3つの名画と
Now, this is a collaboration with three specific famous paintings...
コラボしてるんですが みんな分かるかなー？
but can everyone guess which ones they are?
3つね 3つあるんだけど
Three, there are three of them.
えーでは 左からいきましょうか
Well then, shall we go from the left?
えー左 ターナー『雨、蒸気、速度―グレート・ウェスタン鉄道』
On the left, Turner's "Rain, Steam and Speed - The Great Western Railway".
そして真ん中 モネの『睡蓮の池』
And in the middle, Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond".
そして一番右 これは皆さんお分かりでしょう ゴッホの『ひまわり』
And on the far right, you all probably know this one—van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
そして今回 えーコラボ商品が ございます 全8種類あるんですよー じゃあ1つずつね
And this time, we have collaboration merchandise! There are 8 items in total. Let me introduce them one by one.
ちょっと紹介していきましょうー はい
Let me introduce them to you. Yes.
えーまず左上からいきましょうか
Well, let me start from the top left.
まずはフレグランスミストセットです
First, the Fragrance Mist Set.
らでんが監修考案したフレグランスミスト 3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました
Fragrance mists designed and supervised by Raden. We expressed the impressions of the 3 masterpieces through scents.
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので
These products are alcohol-free fragrance mists, so...
いろんな場面に合わせて使用可能です
you can use them tailored to various occasions!
じゃあ お隣いきましょうか
Now, shall we move to the next one?
えーその隣 ローラーボールペン
Next to it, the Rollerball Pen.
3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を見事に融合させたデザインでございます
A design that beautifully fuses the essence of the three masterpieces with Juufuutei Raden's family crest.
えーじゃあ次は
Well, next...
左下 えーカップ＆ソーサーセット
Bottom left, the Cup & Saucer Set.
描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得たボーンチャイナ製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます
A bone china cup and saucer set inspired by the newly drawn illustrations.
ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています
The center of the saucer also features Juufuutei Raden's name.
最近らでんも紅茶飲むようになったんでお揃いにしましょうや
Lately Raden has started drinking tea too, so let's match!
えーそしてその隣がスカーフ
And next to that is the Scarf.
新たに描き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ
Combining elements from the newly drawn illustrations...
ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます。
This is a designed scarf that combines fashion and practicality.
え、そしてじゃあその隣行こうか。え、アクリルスタンド。本コラボならではの新衣装を身に纏うアクリルスタンドでございます。
Next, moving to the one beside it, the Acrylic Stand! It features the new outfit unique to this collaboration.
えー、じゃあ右上行きましょう！キャンバスアート！描き下ろしイラストが使用されるキャンバスアートでございます。
Now, let's look at the top right! Canvas Art! This canvas art uses an original illustration.
その下はトートバッグ！表面には本コラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には3点の名画のディテールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています。
Below that is the Tote Bag! It features a double-sided design with an original illustration on the front and details from three famous paintings on the back.
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります。全6種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと特別メッセージが入っていますよ！
Finally, the Random Clear Cards! With 6 designs in total, select cards include a foil-stamped digital signature and a special message!
グッズいいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？
Great merch, right? Aren't they all wonderful?
そして…さらに…グッズだけではございません！
And... furthermore... it's not just merch!
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきました！
In collaboration with The National Gallery, London, I recorded an audio guide!
すごーい！
Awesome!
しかも、こちらね、なんと、らんでんの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが、
Furthermore, we plan to upload it on Raden's official channel,
詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちください！
but details will be released at a later date, so please stay tuned!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが、
So, there's plenty of merch and the guide, but...
みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなとこか…ごめんなさい！
Everyone, what kind of place is the National Gallery in London... Sorry!
ちょっと待って！ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか気になりませんか？
Wait a sec! Aren't you curious about what the National Gallery in London is like?
ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Don't you want to see the streets of London?
ということで…なんと、実は！ReGLOSSメンバーでロンドンロケに行ってきましたー！
Therefore... believe it or not, the ReGLOSS members actually went on location in London!
そのロケの様子はReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみに！
Footage of that location shoot will be released on the ReGLOSS channel at a later date, so please look forward to it!
と、いうことで重大告知その2は、儒烏風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとうー！
So, major announcement number 2 was the collaboration between Juufuutei Raden and The National Gallery in London! Thank you!
そして今、スタッフさんの方から…どうやら今、Xで…これXですか？Xでトレンド2位だそうです！すごい！みんなありがとう！
And right now, from the staff... apparently on X... is this X? We're trending #2 on X! Amazing! Thank you everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンド2位に入った理由が「らでんちゃんの体力が心配です」でめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかな？
I wonder if it's okay... What if the reason we're trending #2 is because everyone is tweeting "I'm worried about Raden-chan's stamina"?
でも今日は、今日はもう体力がもうすっからかんになって、次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るって、らでんは決めたんです！
But today, Raden decided to give it her all until her stamina is completely drained and she can't move tomorrow!
だから今日は、みんなもね、いっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです！どうですか皆さん、ついて来れているでしょうか？
So today, I want everyone to enjoy it to the absolute fullest! How is everyone, are you keeping up with me?
重大発表、まだあるんです！まだあるんです！これで終わりじゃないんですよ！
There are still major announcements! There's more! This isn't the end!
しかもライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままで居てくださいね！
Plus, the live concert is still going on, so stay tuned on this channel!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思います！
Now then, I'd like to move on to the next song!
それでは…どうぞ！
With that... please enjoy!
水面に映った藍 眩しく揺れる
Indigo, reflected on the surface of the water, sways dazzlingly.
手探りで探してた 足りない私
I searched by touch for the missing parts of me.
ゆっくりと動き出した 何万年も前から
Everything slowly began to move, from tens of thousands of years ago,
この時を約束されていたみたいに ほら
as if this moment had been promised to me, look.
風は歌い 雨は語り たどり着くよ 光のすみかへ
The wind sings, the rain speaks. I will reach the abode of light.
幾重にも 重なっている この地球の偶然
They are layered one on top of another, the coincidences of this planet.
影の向こう 真実の色 見つけ出すよ 光のすみかを
Beyond the shadows is the true color. I will find the abode of light.
一つでも 欠けていたら きっと出会えてなかったね
If even one thing were missing, I'm sure we would not have met.
飛べぬまま 見上げてた 透明な空から
Unable to fly, I looked up from the clear sky...
透明な空から
From the transparent sky...
真っ直ぐに
...straight down...
差し込んだ
...shone down...
優しい朝日
...the gentle morning sun.
過ぎた季節が歪に
The past seasons irregularly...
削った今という瞬き
...carved this instant called "now."
どこにも同じものはないの
There is nothing the same anywhere.
ほら
Look,
生きてる証
it's proof that we are alive.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
雨は語り
the rain speaks,
たどり着くよ
we will reach it,
光のすみかへ
the abode of light.
幾重にも重なってる
Overlapping in countless layers,
この地球の偶然
the coincidences of this Earth.
影の向こう 真実の色
Beyond the shadows, the color of truth,
見つけ出すよ
we will find it,
光のすみかを
the abode of light.
一つでも欠けていたら
If even one piece had been missing,
きっと
surely...
出会えてなかったね
...we wouldn't have met, right?
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream.
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここでらでんの小咄・美術解説の時間です！
We're in the middle of the live, but now it's time for Raden's short talk and art commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでん！じゃーん！
What I'm introducing this time is this! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ『ひまわり』！
Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
今回、ナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております。ありがとうございます！
We borrowed this image from The National Gallery. Thank you so much!
ゴッホと言えば『ひまわり』というイメージを持っている方も少なくないのではないでしょうか？
Many of you probably associate Van Gogh with "Sunflowers," right?
それもそのはず。実はゴッホの描いた『ひまわり』は一つだけじゃないんです。
And for good reason! Actually, the "Sunflowers" painted by Van Gogh isn't just one.
この世界に失われたものも含めて、7つの『ひまわり』があったんですよ。
Including the ones lost to the world, there were seven "Sunflowers"!
さて、では実際に作品をじっくり見てみましょう！
Now, let's take a closer look at the artwork itself!
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかなー？
What kind of impressions did everyone have?
改めて見ると、色んなことが見えてきます。
Looking at it again, various details start to appear.
よく見ると、ひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで、花びらも不揃いですね。
If you look closely, the sunflower blossoms face different directions, and the petals are uneven too.
しかし、温かな黄色が画面全体を包み込むことで、どこか生命力が溢れているようにも見えませんか？
However, as warm yellow envelops the entire canvas, doesn't it seem bursting with vitality?
ここからは、ゴッホと黄色、そしてゴッホとひまわりについて紐解いていきましょう。
From here, let me untangle the connection between Van Gogh and yellow, as well as Van Gogh and sunflowers.
「太陽は淡い硫黄の輝きを伝達するのだ」という言葉を残しているゴッホは、太陽の光を黄色で表現しました。
Leaving behind the quote "The sun conveys a pale sulfur radiance," Van Gogh expressed sunlight through yellow.
そして黄色はゴッホにとって生命力の象徴でもあります。
And yellow was also a symbol of vitality for Van Gogh.
この絵を描いた時、彼はフランス南部のアルルという街で、心機一転、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと意気込んでいました。
When he painted this, in Arles in southern France, he was eager to make a fresh start and work hard alongside fellow painters.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません。
Perhaps he entrusted those feelings to the color yellow.
一方的で、この絵のモチーフになっているひまわりについて見てみましょう。
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflowers that serve as the motif for this painting.
ひまわりは太陽に向かって咲きます。
Sunflowers bloom facing the sun.
太陽は西洋美術史において「神」を象徴します。
In Western art history, the sun symbolizes "God."
それに向かって咲くひまわりは、崇拝、従順、忠誠、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します。
Blooming towards it, sunflowers symbolize adoration, obedience, loyalty, faith, and love.
ここでさらに遠回りして、彼の過去について知っていきましょう。
Here, let's take a bit of a detour and learn about his past.
先ほどゴッホがアルルでの生活を始めた時、私は「心機一転」という表現をしました。
Earlier, when Van Gogh started his life in Arles, I used the phrase "a fresh start."
実は彼、元々は牧師さんになりたかったんです。
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に注力しますが、上手くいきませんでした。
He worked hard, focusing on his studies and missionary work, but it didn't go well.
画家への転身は、牧師さんへの道を絶たれた後のことだったんですね。
His transition to painter happened after his path to becoming a pastor was cut off.
そんな彼が描く信仰の象徴であるひまわり。
And so, the sunflower—a symbol of faith—painted by such a man.
皆様はどう読み解きますか？
How do you all interpret it?
未来への希望の光？それとも自分への失望？
A ray of hope for the future? Or disappointment in himself?
ゴッホの見た「光のすみか」はひまわりにあったのかもしれませんね。
The "abode of light" that Van Gogh saw might have been in the sunflowers.
という感じのことでございまして、こちらもロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
And that's the story! You can see this painting at The National Gallery in London as well!
ぜひぜひ行ってみてください！
Please do go and check it out!
あ、また次回！
Ah, see you next time!
はい、ということで
Alright, so then...
早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが
Time flies, and the next one will be our final song...
なんと！儒烏風亭らでん
And guess what! Juufuutei Raden...
新曲をリリースしまーす！イエーイ！
...is releasing a brand new song! Yay!
特報！新曲リリース！
Special news! New song release!
タイトルは『Miracle Palette』！
The title is "Miracle Palette"!
はい、えーこちらですね
Yes, here it is.
楽曲リリースなんですが 5月18日の0時00分
As for the song's release, it will be at 00:00 on May 18th,
なので今日の日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます
so it will be released as soon as the date changes today!
5月18日と言えば！そう、皆さん大正解！国際博物館の日でございます！
Speaking of May 18th... Yes, you got it right! It's International Museum Day!
そんな特別な日にリリース！
Releasing on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ！
And right after this stream ends...
MVですね！なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
The MV! Believe it or not, the music video will be released!
儒烏風亭らでん初のダンスてんこ盛り3DMVとなっております！
It's Juufuutei Raden's very first dance-packed 3D MV!
そして、こちら楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね、感じになっております！
And the song concept has a cool, jazzy vibe to it!
ということで
And with that...
今からは、ライブバージョンの『Miracle Palette』を披露したいと思います！
I'd now like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette"!
ダンサーさん、カムオン！
Dancers, come on!
よろしくお願いします！お願いします！
Thank you so much! Looking forward to working with you!
キレキレにしてくれてありがとうございます！
Thank you for those sharp moves!
では、聴いてください。『Miracle Palette』。
Now then, please listen to "Miracle Palette."
暗がりステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Standing on the darkened stage, holding an umbrella,
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
the composition hazy and dim, the impression fleeting.
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin drawing with raindrops.
キャンヴァスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world.
Hop Hop 跳び回る Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす Dance Dance ぐるぐる いざ
Hop Hop, jumping around, Tap Tap, stomping rhythm, Dance Dance, spinning round, now then...
ショータイム！
Showtime!
(Ladies and Gentlemen, Welcome to our magical show!)
スポットライトを浴びて 輝きを放つ
Basking in the spotlight, emanating brilliance.
エンタシスよりプリズム 分光をスタンバイ
Prism over entasis, standby for light dispersion!
(この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう)
(Let us build a seven-colored rainbow bridge across this dull gray sky)
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now, look closely and behold!
目に映るもの、今を彩るから
For everything in sight will color this moment!
大きな絵筆で描き出す 大胆なパースの中 嗚呼
With a big paintbrush, I sketch within a bold perspective, ah...
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
This rain-soaked stage is a miracle palette!
マスカレイドな第二部の開演
The curtain rises on Part 2, a masquerade...
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
From monotone to vivid hues, with asymmetric gradations,
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be completely spellbound.
雨雲にマーブリング
Marbling across the rain clouds,
目を奪われたその隙 イリュージョンをスタンバイ
while your eyes are captivated, standby for illusion!
(ところで皆さん、なくし物はございませんか？)
(By the way, everyone, have you lost anything?)
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome, one and all!
あの手この手で魅了していくから
I will charm you using every trick up my sleeve,
一足お先に まんまと盗みだすわ あなたの心を
and ahead of time, I'll slyly steal your heart away!
光を放ち出す きらめきのパレット
A glittering palette emanating radiant light!
(さてさて！いよいよ大詰め、クライマックスに向けて盛り上がってまいりましょう！)
(Now then, now then! It's the grand finale, let's build up the excitement for the climax!)
Listen!
OK, 5 4 3 2 1 Go on the Show!
最大級のキャンヴァスに描き出す
Drawing upon the grandest canvas,
誰も見たことのない景色
a landscape that no one has ever seen before!
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now, look closely and behold!
次元の壁を超えて閃くから
It flashes bright beyond the dimension wall!
大きな絵筆で描き出す
With a big paintbrush, I sketch...
大胆なパースの中 さあ
In bold perspective, come on!
みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう
Let's all go meet a grand happy ending!
鳴呼 びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
Ah, the drenched stage is a miracle palette!
特報 その③
[Special News Part 3]
ピクセルミュージアム 新情報
[Pixel Museum New Info]
箱根探訪編 DLC
[Hakone Exploration Chapter DLC]
さあさ とくとご覧あれ 目に映るもの 今を彩るから
Come, feast your eyes! What meets your eyes will color the present!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden Guides You: Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 配信決定！
DLC "Hakone Exploration Chapter" release confirmed!
イベント展示のご案内
[Guide to Event Exhibition]
今回のテーマは... 箱根
This time's theme is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意！
We've prepared works related to Curator Raden's beloved Hakone!
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷりと詰まっています！
The museum is also event-themed, packed with Hakone's charm!
もちろん解説はフルボイスでお届けしますよ！
Of course, commentary will be provided fully voiced!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden Guides You: Pixel Museum
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編
DLC: Hakone Exploration Chapter
2026年12月 配信予定
Scheduled for release in December 2026
ちょっと待つだけね〜
Wait just a little bit, okay~
な、な、なんと！
W-W-What?!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに
In less than a year since its release last year on June 5th,
『儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム』の追加ダウンロードコンテンツ『箱根探訪編』の配信が決定いたしました！
the release of the DLC "Hakone Exploration Chapter" for "Juufuutei Raden Guides You: Pixel Museum" has been confirmed!
やったー！
Yay!
みんながいっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、みんなが沢山遊んでくれたおかげです！本当にありがとうございます！
It's all thanks to everyone downloading and playing it so much! Thank you so much!
今回の舞台は皆様おなじみの「箱根」でございます。
The stage this time is the familiar "Hakone".
前作に引き続き、箱根ガラスの森美術館様に加え、
Following the previous title, in addition to the Hakone Glass Museum,
今回はなんと！
this time, amazingly...
ポーラ美術館様と小田急箱根様にもご協力いただけることとなりました！拍手！
Pola Museum of Art and Odakyu Hakone have also agreed to cooperate! Round of applause!
館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート！箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたします。よー、いいでしょう！
The curator's private room has also been updated to the event specification! We'll deliver even more of Hakone's charm. Nice, right?!
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ『箱根探訪編』は、2026年12月に配信予定！
This DLC "Hakone Exploration Chapter" is scheduled for release in December 2026!
さっそくですね、来週5月23日、24日に
And coming right up, next week on May 23rd and 24th,
京都にて開催されますBitSummit 14th Punchにらでピクも登場！
RadePiku will appear at BitSummit 14th Punch held in Kyoto!
大好評発売中のらでピクの試遊や、箱根探訪編のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ！
There will be playtests for the wildly popular RadePiku and distribution of key visual postcards for the Hakone Exploration Chapter!
詳しい情報は公式ホームページとJupiterさんの公式Xを要チェックです！
Be sure to check the official homepage and Jupiter's official X for details!
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも？
There might still be more exciting news?
それではリリースまでお楽しみに！
So please look forward to the release!
はい！そしてそして、皆様お待たせ！
Yes! And next, what you've all been waiting for!
儒烏風亭らでん100万人記念グッズが発売されます！
Juufuutei Raden 1M Commemoration Merch is going on sale!
ごめんね、今日本当になんか発表が多くて...
Sorry, there are really so many announcements today...
さっそく詳細見ていきましょう。1つ目はこちら、デン！
Let's check out the details right away. First up is this, ta-da!
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック
Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block
あ、めっちゃ疲れてるらでん映ってた...
Ah, a super tired Raden was shown...
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック！
Live in New Outfit! Acrylic Block!
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん。
Raden in new outfit singing happily on the live stage.
森倉円先生の描き下ろしでございます。いいでしょう！
Drawn by Morikura En-sensei. Isn't it great?
こちらアクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されておりまして、
This is printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block,
めっちゃね、奥行きが感じられるものとなっておるんですよ！
and you can really feel the depth in it!
らでんの衣装いろいろ3連結アクリルキーホルダー
Raden's Outfits Various 3-Connected Acrylic Keychain
新衣装、通常衣装、フラッシュポイント衣装の3種類の3連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております。
It's a 3-connected acrylic keychain featuring 3 outfits: new outfit, standard outfit, and Flash Point outfit.
イラストはココロパズルリズムの時の、あのね後ろに可愛いイラスト流れていたんですけれども、
The illustration is from Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm, when those cute illustrations were playing in the background,
でお馴染み、つぼみく先生でございます！
by the familiar Tsubomiku-sensei!
続いてこちら、デン！
Next up is this, ta-da!
新衣装モチーフピンバッジセット
New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set
懐中時計、マスク、シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております！
It comes in 4 types: pocket watch, mask, top hat, and monocle!
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next up is this, ta-da!
「ライブ前のトラブル！？」ボイス！らでんが書き下ろした台本です！
"Trouble Before the Live Stream!?" Voice! Script written by Raden!
どんな方かは聴いてみてのお楽しみ！
Look forward to listening to see what it's like!
そして、フルセット購入特典はこちら！えいっ！
And here is the full set purchase bonus! Ta-da!
はい！えー、儒烏風亭らデン直筆サイン入りモリクラエン先生描き下ろしポストカード！
Yes! A postcard illustrated by Morikura En-sensei, autographed by Juufuutei Raden!
今回も購入された方全員に直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
This time too, I will personally hand-sign each one for everyone who purchases it!
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、よろしくお願いいたします！
I'll do my best signing every single one so it reaches you, so please look forward to it!
さらに特典ボイスも付きます！こちらもらデンが書き下ろしてます！
Plus, a bonus voice clip is included! I wrote the script for this one as well!
はい！ということで...
Alright, so...
今日ね、もう、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが...
Today was really packed with so much content, but...
皆さん追いつけてますか？
...are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもない発表をたくさんしたんですけれど...
I made a lot of pretty huge announcements,
らデンが一番結構とんでもないなと思っております！
...and I think I'm the one who's most blown away by them!
ということで！本日の重大発表は、その1：東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ！
So, today's major announcements are: Part 1, a collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum!
その2：ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ！
Part 2, a collaboration with the National Gallery in London!
その3：儒烏風亭らデンがご案内！ピクセルミュージアムDLC発売決定でございます！
Part 3, DLC for Pixel Museum guided by Juufuutei Raden has been confirmed for release!
情報量が多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみてください！
I know that was a lot of info to process, so please double-check the stream archive as well!
そしてこの後は、メン限でアンコールライブあります！
And after this, we have a member-exclusive encore live stream!
その時にまた衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っております。
I'm planning to take my time showing off the new outfit then.
まだの方はチャンネル登録と、気になった方はメンバーでまたお会いしましょう！
So if you haven't yet, subscribe, and if you're interested, join as a member and see you at the encore live!
そしてそして！忘れちゃいけません！この後すぐ、新曲MV公開でございます！
And also, don't forget! Right after this, my new song's music video will be released!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいです！
We put a lot of work into it, so I really hope you watch it a lot!
日頃応援してくださっている皆様、聴いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで...
Thanks to all of you who support me every day, watching and listening, my dear listeners...
今回このライブを開催することができました！
...we were able to hold this live stream today!
本当に本当にありがとうございます！とっても嬉しいです！
Thank you so very, very much! I'm so happy!
これからも歌もダンスも自分のやりたいこともいっぱい頑張っていきますので...
Going forward, I'll keep working hard on my singing, dancing, and everything I want to do...
ぜひ応援のほどよろしくお願いいたします！
...so please keep supporting me!
それでは！メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう！
With that, see you all in the member-exclusive encore live!
本日のお相手は私、儒烏風亭らデンでございました！
Your host today was Juufuutei Raden!
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください！
Have a wonderful night, everyone!
さようならデン！
Sayona-raden!